Good morning.
Good morning. My name is Dan Margulies and Rabbi Linzer is away.
Michal will be back on Sunday and today we get to start
the fifth פרק, perek, היו בודקין Hayu Bodkin right at the top
of מ עמוד א Mem Amud Aleph with the משנה. Mishnah. We're
going to go through the whole פרק perek of משנה Mishnah because
that occupies most of our דף daf here and then we'll get
into the סוגיות. sugyot. So we're really in the middle of a
subject here but we're switching from the beginnings of the process that
we discussed somewhat in the last פרק, perek, the process of accepting
the witnesses and the court proceeding and here we discuss specifically the
rules of the חקירות chakiros and the דרישות drishot or בדיקות, bedikos,
different types of questions that can come up that the court has
to ask the witnesses. Some of them are more mandatory, some of
them are more optional, some of them are more precise types of
questions that if the witnesses get them wrong, the whole testimony is
disqualified and some of them
even if the witnesses don't know the right answer or there's some
disagreement about them, it'll be alright. And this is particularly for דיני
נפשות, Dinei Nefashot, that is, we don't have a process of דרישה
וחקירה drisha ve-chakira applied to דיני ממונות. Dinei Mamonos. We learned that
already in the first פרק perek and that was more not because
it would be mandatory from the Torah's laws but because the Rabbis
realized that it would become too difficult for people to have civil
suits if all of the witnesses had to be interrogated to this
extent. It would make the legal proceedings too difficult, people would lose
money, and that was a big problem the Rabbis saw. So the
משנה Mishnah says היו בודקין אותן בשבע חקירות. hayu bodkin otan be-sheva
chakirot. They, that is the judges, would interrogate the witnesses with seven
different types
of חקירות chakirot and the משנה Mishnah lists them: באיזו שבוע, be-eizo
shavua, in which cycle of seven years during the יובל Yovel cycle?
That is שבוע, shavua, שבוע shavua in the משנה Mishnah very often
refers to a group of seven years, the שמיטה Shmita cycle. So
which week of years that is within the יובל Yovel cycle? באיזו
שנה, be-eizo shana, and which year within the cycle of seven? באיזו
חודש, be-eizo chodesh, and which month during the year? בכמה בחודש, be-khamma
ba-chodesh, which day of the month? באיזו יום, be-eizo yom, and which
day of the week? באיזו שעה, be-eizo sha'ah, and at what hour
of the day? Okay and the seventh one, so six questions about
time: באיזו שעה ובאיזו מקום, be-eizo sha'ah u-ve-eizo makom, and in what
place? Interesting to think about, you know, our questions, we have six
plus one. I'm thinking here it's ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, we're also
thinking about six plus one cycles of time and things like that,
so it's interesting the way they fit together. באיזו מקום, be-eizo makom,
what place is it? Is that very general, it was in New
York City? Does that have to be it was in Riverdale, it
was in the second or third floor of the בית, bayit, something
like that? So all sorts of questions, how precise do these have
to be, are going to get raised as well. רבי יוסי אומר
באיזו יום באיזו שעה באיזו מקום. Rabbi Yose omer be-eizo yom be-eizo
sha'ah be-eizo makom. Rabbi Yose says you only need to ask three
חקירות, chakirot, that is which day of the week and at what
hour and in what place. Now the משנה Mishnah continues and says
different questions that have to be asked and this is a debate
whether these are part of the חקירות chakirot or not. In fact,
if you look in the רמב"ם's Rambam פירוש המשניות, Perush ha-Mishnayos, the
רמב"ם Rambam there says and it's the opinion of רבינו דוד Rabbeinu
David as well, that these questions we're going to read are even
more important, they precede the חקירות chakirot because these aren't questions that
would be used to invalidate the witnesses or not but these are
actually questions without which there's no testimony at all, that is the
content of the testimony itself is part and parcel of these questions.
And those questions are מכירין אתם אותו, makirin atem oto, do you,
the witnesses, know him? We're going to see that that means were
you able to recognize who this person was particularly whether it was
a Jewish person or a non-Jewish person. התריתם בו, hitartem bo, did
you provide התראה? hasra'ah? Did you warn him about the consequences of
performing this action? Right, we're talking specifically here about דיני נפשות, Dinei
Nefashot, so someone is about to worship an idol and the witnesses
have to say, you know, if you're going to worship this idol
you're going to be punished by סקילה. skila. So something like that.
Okay. And then further the details of the act that took place.
העובד עבודה זרה, ha-oved avodah zarah, if someone was worshipping idolatry, את
מי עבד, et mi avad, which idolatry did he worship? ובמה עבד,
u-ve-mah avad,
and which type of activity did he use to worship it? Because
we know the we're going to get to this as well soon,
עבודה זרה avodah zarah is characterized by two different possibilities in terms
of how the worship takes place. Number one are four general types
of worship that are prohibited for every type of עבודה זרה avodah
zarah even if it's not the normal way it's worshipped. That would
be bringing a sacrifice, pouring out libations,
sacrificing incense, and then bowing to it. Those four things because those
are things that we do in our service of God. If you
do it for an idol or you do it for a false
religion, it demonstrates that you're using a Jewish mode of worship or
a universal mode of worship in the worship of that עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, so that would be punishable. As well, if this עבודה
זרה Avodah Zarah has a characteristic way of being worshipped. For example,
the גמרא's Gemara classic example is מרקוליס. Markulis. מרקוליס Markulis is probably
the Roman God Mercury was worshipped by throwing stones or placing stones
at a particular location, either where the idol was located or even
just at a crossroads and things like that. So if you throwed
a stone at מרקוליס, Markulis, even if you thought that you were
doing it just to make fun of it, "Oh, I'm going to
throw a rock at it as a sign of disgrace," because that's
the way it's normally worshipped, that would also be punishable. So either
of those. So במה עבד, Bameh Avad, that's in what way did
you serve the idol? And then the משנה Mishna says כל המרבה
בבדיקות הרי זה משובח. Kol hamarbeh bivdikot harei zeh meshubach. So if
you increase further questions, that's praiseworthy. So that is the בדיקות Bdikot
are different than חקירות. Chakiros. בדיקות Bdikot are just the sort of
questions that can come up and the משנה's Mishna going to clarify.
Just one point, רש"י Rashi makes a very big deal about here
is that the purpose of the חקירות, Chakiros, at least according to
רש"י, Rashi, is particularly to create a context for עדות שיכול להזימה.
Edut sheyachol lehazimah. That is testimony which has the potential to be
confirmed as a conspiratorial testimony. That is, we know we're going to
get soon, in only a few months, to מסכת מכות, Masechet Makkos,
the first פרק Perek in מסכת מכות Masechet Makkos deals with the
question of conspiring witnesses, עדים זוממים, Edim zomemim, and one of the
core way of turning the testimony or turning the witnesses into עדים
זוממים Edim zomemim is by saying עמנו הייתם, Imanu hayitem, "You, the
witnesses, were actually with us in a different place at the same
time," and therefore you couldn't have witnessed the crime. So for that
to be when we say עדות שיכול להזימה, Edut sheyachol lehazimah, the
testimony could be confirmed to be a conspiratorial, it means that you
have to know at what place and at what time the event
took place. That's a particularly, so it's not just necessarily, meaning we
could if if we were a hundred percent sure that a person
violated a certain מצוה, Mitzvah, they worshipped עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, something
like that, but we don't know when and we don't know where.
Okay. Knowing when and where is not part of the עבירה. Aveira.
Knowing when and where is about the quality of the testimony so
that we can confirm the truth of the testimony and have that
safeguard on the legal process. So רש"י Rashi emphasizes that. So we
said כל המרבה בבדיקות הרי זה משובח. Kol hamarbeh bivdikot harei zeh
meshubach. If you add on further questions, that's also praiseworthy. And the
משנה Mishna says מעשה ובדק בן זכאי בעוקצי תאנים. Maaseh uvadak Ben
Zakkai be'uktzei te'einim. And there was a case of רבי יוחנן בן
זכאי Rabbi Yochanan Ben Zakkai who asked a בדיקה Bdikah question. בדיקות,
Bdikot, we said, are the non-mandatory questions, it's sort of part of
the discretion of the court about the stems of the figs. That
is, there was a murder that took place under a fig tree
and בן זכאי Ben Zakkai asked the witnesses, "Did the fig tree
have thicker stems or thinner stems?" Different types of figs have different
kinds of stems. And that question, that בדיקה, Bdikah, was used to
confirm whether or not those two witnesses really were there at the
correct place and the same place to make sure the witnesses their
testimony agreed. Both witnesses would have to answer correctly.
And they interrogated the witnesses separately?
Of course they have to be interrogated separately. Right. And actually when
we hear the testimony as well, we hear the testimony separately, but
they have to be close to each other, but the interrogation has
to be done really so that they can't overhear. Obviously, that each
independent witness, if we're going to confirm that they saw the event
and they're not conspiring, we have to be able to investigate them
carefully. And the משנה Mishna continues מה בין חקירות לבדיקות. Mah bein
chakiros livdikot. What's the difference between חקירות Chakiros and בדיקות? Bdikot? Because
the משנה Mishna has started with חקירות. Chakiros. חקירות, Chakiros, אחד אומר
איני יודע עדותן בטילה. Echad omer eini yodeiah edutan beteilah. For the
חקירה Chakira questions, the first set of questions about when and where
it took place and perhaps the questions about did you warn him
and what type of which type of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah it
was and things like that.
So those questions, if even one of the witnesses says איני יודע,
Eini yodeiah, "I don't know," עדותן בטילה, Edutan beteilah, the entire testimony
is thrown out because that would make a hole in the believability
of the testimony because it would not be עדות שיכול להזימה. Edut
sheyachol lehazimah. We would not have the potential for הזמה. Hazamah. If
you say, "I don't know what day of the week it was,"
well then you've left yourself open. No one can come and say,
"Oh, on Tuesday you were in, you know, Queens so you couldn't
have been in in Manhattan." So that would be problematic, okay.
But בדיקות, Bdikot, אחד אומר איני יודע ואפילו שנים אומרים אין אנו
יודעים עדותן קיימת. Echad omer eini yodeiah va'afilu shenayim omrim ein anu
yode'im edutan kayamet. But בדיקות Bdikot questions like רבי יוחנן בן זכאי's
Rabbi Yochanan Ben Zakkai question about the fig stems, if one of
them says, "I don't know," or even both of them say, "I
don't know," then it's fine because those questions aren't integral to the
to the quality of the testimony. So for example, the fig stems,
if one of them said it was thick stems and one said
thin stems, then we know that they're lying because they couldn't have
been talking about the same tree. Of course, the thick and thin
have to have some objective determining factor. Maybe it was white figs
and black figs or something like that, the stems are different colors.
But if one of them says, "Oh, they were thick stems," and
one of them says, "I don't know what kind of stems, I
wasn't paying attention to the fig tree, I was paying attention to
the murder," then it's fine. attention to the murder, then that would
be okay because the בדיקות bedikot questions are meant to catch them
in a contradiction, not to affirm the realities of the testimony. Okay.
The משנה mishna continues אחד חקירות ואחד בדיקות, echad chakirot ve'echad bedikot,
but חקירות chakirot and בדיקות bedikot questions בזמן שמכחישים זה את זה,
bizman shemachchishim ze et ze, if they contradict each other, עדותן בטלה,
edutan betela, then the testimony is thrown out. That is the purpose
of בדיקות bedikot is to catch you in a contradiction, the purpose
of the חקירה chakira is to catch you even with a lack
of knowledge. אחד אומר בשניים בחודש ואחד אומר בשלושה בחודש, echad omer
bishnayim bachodesh ve'echad omer bishlosha bachodesh, what if one of the witnesses
said it took place on the second day of the month and
one said it's on the third day of the month? עדותן קיימת,
edutan kayemet, then the testimony is upheld. שזה יודע בעיבורו של חודש
וזה אינו יודע בעיבורו של חודש, sheze yode'a be'iburo shel chodesh veze
eino yode'a be'iburo shel chodesh, because they have a disagreement or maybe
they one of them was unaware that the בית דין beit din
that the previous month has 30 days or 29 days. So particularly,
and we see here the example is the second and the third
days of the month, that is early on in the month people
may have been confused about which day of the month it was
because the months were variable with the exception, as maybe we're familiar,
with the month of אלול Elul that since the times of עזרא,
Ezra, the month of אלול Elul never had 30 days. It was
always 29 days.
But so a person could be off by one day and we
wouldn't be suspicious that they were lying or that they really weren't
there because early on in the month there could be some flexibility.
זה אומר בשלושה ואחד אומר בחמישה, ze omer bishlosha ve'echad omer bachamisha,
what if one says it was on the third of the month,
one says on the fifth of the month, then עדותן בטלה edutan
betela because it's impossible that they could be off by two days
because the months will always be either 29 or 30 days. And
this is proof is that a normal respectable person who's going to
be coming to court to testify has to keep track of which
day of the month it is. Very often you stop someone in
the street and say, oh, which day of אלול Elul is it,
or which day of תמוז Tammuz is it, or whatever, people may
not be so careful with that nowadays. But people are usually familiar
with the Gregorian calendar. So in one way or another we do
have a sense of the passage of the days of the month.
Okay. Sort of.
Today's the third
of אלול, Elul, it's the 25th of August.
Okay. So now we get into the question of hours and this
is a question with some interesting implications for פסח Pesach as well
as תוספות Tosafot raises. אחד אומר בשתי שעות ואחד אומר בשלוש שעות.
echad omer bishtei sha'ot ve'echad omer bishalosh sha'ot. One says it was
in the second hour and one says it was in the third
hour of the day, עדותן קיימת. edutan kayemet. You could be off
by one hour and that's a reasonable error on the part of
a human being. This is not so much about anything the court
has done, but that's just because they didn't have watches or clocks,
they used the sun, so the variability between the second and third
hour would be a normal mistake.
אחד אומר בשלוש ואחד אומר בחמש, echad omer bishalosh ve'echad omer bachamesh,
but if one person said it was in the third hour, one
says it's in the fifth hour, עדותן בטלה. edutan betela. Being off
by two hours, that is or maybe each of them is off
by one hour in each direction, that already is too much.
Okay, but רבי יהודה אומר קיימת. Rabbi Yehuda omer kayemet. רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says that that would be acceptable because רבי יהודה's Rabbi
Yehuda position would be even a two hour error is a reasonable
amount of error. And that gets into תוספות Tosafot raises the question,
how does that apply to some of the questions we have about
beginning of פסח? Pesach? We know that the biblical prohibition, the דאורייתא
de'oraita prohibition on eating חמץ chametz kicks in at noon on ערב
פסח erev Pesach because the afternoon of the day has to be
a period where we don't have any חמץ chametz so that we
can we can bring the קרבן פסח korban Pesach because לא תשחט
על חמץ דם זבחי. lo tishchat al chametz dam zivchi. But the
sixth hour is a rabbinic prohibition lest we come into the seventh
hour, the second half of the day. And the fifth hour there's
a prohibition on eating חמץ chametz but not on owning the חמץ.
chametz. And that's a prohibition the גמרא Gemara says because of perhaps
it would be a cloudy day and you'll make a mistake between
the fifth hour and the sixth hour. So it sounds like it's
a rabbinic prohibition safeguarding another rabbinic prohibition which usually we don't say.
We don't say גוזרים גזירה על הגזירה. gozrim gezeira al hagezeira. So
there are many different explanations and perhaps the fifth hour is really
protection for the seventh hour, but then it becomes a two hour
protection which seems to be something that the חכמים Chachamim would not
think is a normal mistake, but רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda does think
is a normal kind of mistake. So those are some interesting questions
there about also the question of if it's around noon where we
can tell whether the sun is directly overhead is also a different
point. Like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would distinguish between the third and
the fifth is a normal mistake, but between the fifth and the
seventh where the sun has gone from the eastern side to the
western side would not be a normal type of mistake.
Okay.
אחד אומר בחמש ואחד אומר בשבע, echad omer bachamesh ve'echad omer besheva,
right that's what I just said, if according even רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda agrees if it was if one says it was in the
fifth hour and one says it's in the seventh hour, עדותן בטלה.
edutan betela. Then that will be thrown out because even according to
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that's an unreasonable error to make. שבחמש
חמה במזרח, shebachamesh chama bamizrach, in the fifth hour the sun is
in the east, ובשבע חמה במערב, ubesheva chama bama'arav, the sun will
be in the west already afternoon. ואחר כך, ve'achar kach, so now
after we've performed the different questions, interrogations, cross-examination of
the witnesses. אם נמצאו דבריהם מכוונים, Im nimtze'u divreihem mechuvannim, if we
see that their answers correspond, פותחין בזכות, potchin bizchut, we first open
with an assumption even though we have two witnesses now who are
testifying that this person is guilty, we still try to open up
the possibility for acquittal. אם אחד מן העדים יש לו ללמד עליו
זכות, Im echad min ha'edim yesh lo lelamed alav z'chut, if one
of the witnesses says I know some reason why we could acquit
him, או אחד מן התלמידים יש לומר עליו חובה, o echad min
ha'talmidim yesh lomar alav chova, משתקין אותו. meshatkin oto. But and if
one of the students, that is people observing the case, not one
of the judges, says I know reason why he's liable, משתקין אותו.
meshatkin oto. Either of those we silence them. Part of that is
because the witnesses, once they've come to testify that the person is
guilty, the witnesses are no longer able to change their testimony to
say, oh I have another reason to say that actually he's innocent.
That is, you wouldn't have come to court and testified and everything.
We have a general principle, כיוון שהגיד שוב אינו חוזר ומגיד, keivan
she'higid shuv eino chozer u'magid, that is once you already entered your
testimony in the docket, you can't retract it and go back and
add further testimony. So that's part of it. But perhaps also, why
did you first come in and say the person is guilty and
now you're saying, oh really I know a reason why he's innocent?
It's like it's so contradictory to think what kind of a person
could say that. If you're testifying the person is liable for capital
crime, it must mean you really should be a hundred percent sure
of it, so we would be so suspicious of someone who'd be
doing that. But for one of the תלמידים, talmidim, if one of
the junior judges to insert himself and ללמד עליו חובה lelamed alav
chova to say a reason why he's guilty, we also quiet them
up because for the judges we want to start off the
judicial proceedings always with the acquittal rather than finding him guilty. Okay.
משתקין אותו. meshatkin oto. אמר אחד מן התלמידים יש לי ללמד עליו
זכות. Amar echad min ha'talmidim yesh li lelamed alav z'chut. So one
of the תלמידים talmidim says, I have a reason why we should
find him innocent, מעלין אותו. maalin oto. We bring him up into
the court. That is the תלמיד talmid can enter into with the
other judges because he has a reason to acquit. That is, he
was left off of the bench for this one, but because he
thinks he has a reason to acquit, so it's very biased. We
know this whole talmudic system of court cases for capital crimes is
very biased towards the side of זכות. z'chut. We know that's based
on the מצוה mitzvah of והצילו העדה, v'hitzilu ha'edah, the community has
an obligation to save the person. It's learned from the case of
the עיר מקלט ir miklat involuntary manslaughter, but is extended to every
single capital crime that we have a prerogative and an injunction that
we have a requirement to try to save the person and find
them innocent rather than finding him guilty. Okay.
So these תלמידים talmidim are sort of like
they're sort of people who could have been judges that are observing
the case, but if one of them raises their hand and says,
oh you know really, you know I thought of...
So they're in the בית מדרש beit midrash learning or something?
Well so they're but they're participating in the court case in some
way. You know there's what better way to learn the law than
by observing it in action, right? So and obviously if their teachers
and their רבנים rebbeim are on the בית דין, Beit Din, then
the best way for them to be observing and learning the הלכה
halacha from them is to see them dealing with a real case.
But it's a good question why is it that they're having a
practical session rather than a theoret- you know, that's part of the
whole whole thing. Law is lived in the courtroom. Okay.
So if one of the תלמידים talmidim says יש לי ללמד עליו
זכות, yesh li lelamed alav z'chut, מעלין אותו ומושיבין אותו ביניהם, maalin
oto u'moshivin oto beineihem,
ולא היה יורד משם כל היום כולו. v'lo haya yored misham kol
ha'yom kulo. And he wouldn't go down for the rest of the
day. Okay. That is once he gets appointed to the bench with
other judges he stays up there. אם יש ממש בדבריו, Im yesh
mamash b'divrav, if there's some truth to what he's saying, שומעין לו,
shomin lo, then they can listen they should listen to him. אפילו
הוא אומר יש לי ללמד על עצמי זכות, Afilu hu omer yesh
li lelamed al atzmi z'chut, and even if the accused says I
have a reason to defend myself and he has some claim that
should support himself, שומעין לו, shomin lo, we can listen to him.
Now it's interesting there is usually we don't accept testimony from the
parties to the case. It's not really how our system works. You
can't testify about yourself. But if you have some some claim, we
sort of we think, okay, if this person has some other piece
of evidence, some other claim that's going to influence the way the
judges would decide, even then we can insert it in as well.
Okay. ובלבד שיש ממש בדבריו, U'vilvad she'yesh mamash b'divrav, as long as
there's some truth to what he's saying or some substance to it.
Obviously you can't stay the case forever just by claiming, oh I
have another reason to think that I'm innocent, and then there's really
nothing. So you sort of get to a boy who cried wolf
situation where at some point we're going to stop listening to you
if there's no reason to trust that what you're saying is meaningful.
So he's not he's not testifying as a witness. He's
sort of like a pseudo-judge at that point.
Something like that. It's sort of a different stage of the proceedings.
Right. And it's interesting, you know, part of the question the ראשונים
Rishonim deal with is already like, well what is that? Why is
this even allowed? Or what, you know, what role is he playing?
So it sort of is because of its even circumstantial evidence already
at this point, if it's going to tip the scales towards innocence,
that's what we want. So it's sort of just another opening there
within the system. אם מצאו לו זכו פטרוהו. Im matzu lo zechu
petaruhu. If they find a reason why he's innocent, פטרוהו, petaruhu, they
would let him go free. ואם לאו, Ve'im lav, but if they
didn't find any reason to find him innocent, מעבירין אותו למחר. maavirin
oto lemachar. Still they stay the final deliberations until tomorrow. What would
they do? מזדווגים זוגות זוגות. Mizdavvegim zugot zugot. The judges would join
up pair by pair. Now it's interesting, we have to have an
odd-numbered court, so how would they do pair by pair if there's
an odd number? Every Talmud teacher knows when you break up into
חברותא chavrusa and you have an even-numbered class, it's always a problem.
So I think it means there must have been one group of
three at least. היו ממעטים במאכל, Hayu memaatim bemaachal, they would eat
less, that is to try to not indulge themselves or have a
luxurious day, but they really have a very weighty task at hand.
ולא היו שותים יין כל היום, Velo hayu shotin yayin kol hayom,
and they couldn't drink wine all day. We know that a judge
is disallowed from rendering a decision while having consumed alcohol. So here
we see that that rule is in effect throughout the entire period
of the deliberation. כל היום ונושאים ונותנים כל הלילה, Kol hayom venose'in
venotenin kol halayla, the entire day, and the pairs presumably would discuss
amongst themselves the details of the case, משא ומתן masa umatan back
and forth the entire night. כל הלילה, Kol halayla, I saw on
Facebook some people had a little bit of a discussion about the
דף יומי Daf Yomi and one was saying, oh it means they
didn't sleep the entire night. I wasn't sure about that. It says
נושאים ונותנים כל הלילה. nose'in venotenin kol halayla. כל הלילה, Kol halayla,
does that mean really the entire night they have to be involved
in the discussion or does it mean even if they go to
sleep, but more or less they're occupied in the discussion of the
case as much of the night as possible? We know the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol has to stay up the entire night before יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. Perhaps it's something similar going on here as well.
There's some parallelism between כהן גדול Kohen Gadol going in to do
the עבודה avoda on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and the judges going
in for a capital case. There's some parallelism there, something to think
about. Okay. ולמחרת, Ulemacharat, also you know they reduce the amount of
food that they eat and things like that, something similar to the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and to יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. ולמחרת, Ulemacharat,
on the next day, that is the second day of the case,
משכימים, mashkimim, they wake up early ובאים לבית דין uba'in lebeit din
and they come to the בית דין. beit din. המזכה אומר, Hamezakeh
omer, so one who thinks that the person is innocent says, אני
מזכה ומזכה אני במקומי. Ani mezakeh umezakeh ani bimkomi. He says, I
find this person innocent and I was saying innocent already yesterday, I
remain in my place, that is my position didn't change. והמחייב אומר,
Vehamachayev omer, and one who's saying that he's guilty says, אני מחייב
ומחייב אני במקומי. Ani machayev umachayev ani bimkomi. I'm saying he's guilty
and I'm remaining in my place, that is I didn't change from
yesterday. But what if someone changed their mind? המלמד חובה מלמד זכות.
Hamlamed chova melamed zechut. One who used to say guilty yesterday could
have been convinced now to say innocent. אבל Aval המלמד זכות אינו
יכול לחזור ללמד חובה. hamlamed zechut eino yachol lachzor lelamed chova. Someone
who yesterday said innocent can't change, cannot be convinced to change to
guilty. That is, even from the initial deliberations the first day, you
can already get a chance to see the fact that the judges
cannot switch their, they can switch a verdict from guilty to innocent,
but they can't switch from innocent to guilty. So that's also going
to result in an interesting catch-22, which is that we know if
the entire court agrees the person is guilty, they also don't get
punished, right? We don't execute someone with a unanimous verdict. So what
if the entire court ruled he was guilty the first day and
then some of them switched over to say he was innocent? Well,
that would be allowed, but that would actually result in a switch
from the verdict being to not to execute to being to execute.
So I don't know, I've thought about that, it's sort of a
catch-22, I'm not sure what the פסק psak would actually be in
such a case. Okay.
Why is it that if it's unanimous they wouldn't execute?
There's been some statistical discussion about this about sort of how convinced
people are of things and how suspicious it is. And you can
imagine if you're able to convince 23 people of something,
so either you say, oh it must be that he's totally guilty
and it's so obvious, but part of it also is that there's
a fear of groupthink and that if every single person in a
court is convinced unanimously that this person is guilty, we throw out
the case because we maybe were concerned that the judges felt so
intimidated one from another that they couldn't decide honestly, that they, or
they were worried that there was some external pressure or some bias
that's convincing all of them to rule that he's guilty. It makes
it more suspicious. And there's been some statistical analysis about that from
even in all other sorts of contexts where if it's really across
the board, you get a 100%, there's something fishy going on. So
that's a little interesting piece of it, but part of it also
is just sort of based on perhaps גזירת הכתוב, gezirat hakatuv, but
perhaps it's also based on sort of the realities of those situations
we're worried about the groupthink and things like that. Okay, the משנה
Mishnah continues, we're almost done with the משנה. Mishnah. טעו בדבר, Ta'u
bidvar, so if one of the judges made a mistake about his
own ruling from yesterday, that is, what if someone who had said
innocent then tried to switch to guilty? But then we make sure,
so שני סופרי הדיינים מזכירין אותו. shenei sofrei hadayanim mazkirin oto. We
have two scribes keeping track for the court,
the clerks. So the clerks' job is to make sure that the
judges don't change their rulings in a way that's not allowed. אם
מצאו לו זכות, Im matzu lo zechut, if they rule that he's
innocent, פטרוהו, petaruhu, they set him free. ואם לאו, Ve'im lav, and
if they did not find him innocent, it's interesting again, similar, the
גמרא Gemara discusses often in the תורה, Torah, we see the phrase
לא טהור. lo tahor. Something is not pure. So here, they did
not find him innocent. It's a similar kind of thing, taking this
circuitous description in order to not say that he's guilty. ואם לאו,
Ve'im lav, they didn't find him innocent, עומדים למנין. omdim leminyan. Then
they get up to do a vote. That is, they do a
first sort of a roll call vote, but we don't actually keep
track of how many people say. Now, in the final stage, we
do מנין, minyan, we actually count the number of votes. שנים עשר
מזכין ואחד עשר מחייבין. Shenayim asar mazakin ve'achad asar mechayavin.
If 12 people say he's innocent and 11 say he's guilty, זכאי.
zakai. So 12 against 11, 12 innocent is innocent because it's a
majority. שנים עשר מחייבין ואחד עשר מזכין Shenayim asar mechayavin ve'achad asar
mazakin and 12 guilty and 11 innocent, ואפילו אחד עשר מזכין ואחד
עשר מחייבין ואחד אומר איני יודע, ve'afilu achad asar mazakin ve'achad asar
mechayavin ve'echad omer eini yodea, or even 11 guilty, 11 innocent, and
one abstain, a judge says I don't know, אפילו עשרים ושנים מזכין
afilu esrim ushenayim mazakin או מחייבין o mechayavin or 22 say guilty
ואחד אומר איני יודע ve'echad omer eini yodea
and one says I don't know, then יוסיפו הדיינים. yosifu hadayanim. Then
you have to add on judges. If there's someone who says I
don't know, I can't decide, you have to add in more judges.
Now, I don't understand, how is that going to solve the problem?
If one person says I don't know the right ruling and then
you add two more judges or you add five more judges, six
more judges, whatever, it's not going to affect that person's ruling, it
seems. So how will that really solve the problem? It's not sure.
We'll get into that. וכמה מוסיפין, Vechamah mosifin, and how many do
they add? שנים שנים. shenayim shenayim. You add two, two and two
further every time עד שבעים ואחד ad shivim ve'echad until the court
reaches a number 71. 71 is the largest court that we can
have, so you can't add any more than that. And at that
point, if you have 71, שלושים ושישה מזכין ושלושים וחמישה מחייבין, sheloshim
veshishah mazakin usheloshim vechamishah mechayavin,
if you have 36 that say innocent and 35 who say guilty,
זכאי. zakai. Then he's innocent. שלושים ושישה מחייבין, Sheloshim veshishah mechayavin, 36
say guilty, ושלושים וחמישה מזכין, usheloshim vechamishah mazakin, if
you have 36 who say guilty and 35 who say innocent, דנין
אלו כנגד אלו עד שיראה אחד מן המחייבין דברי המזכין. danin elu
keneged elu ad sheyireh echad min hamechayavin divrei hamazakin. Then they try
to convince each other so that one of the ones who says
guilty will switch to the innocent side. That is what? You have
a deadlock because we can't execute you without a majority of three.
So 36 to 35 wouldn't work, it needs to be 37 against
34 in order to execute.
But we also can't throw out the case and say you're innocent
because the majority ruled that you're guilty. So we're in a deadlock.
So in order to resolve the deadlock, we try to have the
judges voting innocent try to convince the side who are guilty. It's
sort of a filibuster kind of a case.
Yeah, so in the בית דין Beit Din of 23, 13 to
10 would
be, 13 to 10 is what you need to execute.
Right, because of the...
and that's why the examples in the משנה Mishnah you have 12
against 11. With 12 against 11, you can't do anything and with
12 against 11 another way, you're innocent and so we saw that
before. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara now discusses the origin of the
חקירות. chakirot. But before we do that, I just want to read
the רמב"ם Rambam to somewhat quickly summarize. This is in the first
chapter of הלכות עדות. Hilchot Edut. The רמב"ם Rambam points out exactly
what we're discussing. הלכה ד' מצות עשה לדרוש העדים ולחקור אותם. Halacha
dalet: Mitzvat aseh lidrosh ha'edim velachkor otam. There's a positive mitzvah on
the court to do the דרישה, derishah, investigation, and חקירה, chakirah, the
cross-examination. Maybe you want to translate those words, דרישה derishah and חקירה.
chakirah. ולהרבות בשאלתן, Uleharbot bish'elatan, and we have to ask many questions.
ומדקדקין עליהם, Umedakdekin aleihem, we're very exacting with them. ומשיאין אותם מענין
לענין בתוך השאלה. Umasi'in otam me'inyan le'inyan betoch hashe'elah. We try to
confuse them by switching which types of subjects we're asking the questions
about while we're asking them כדי שישתוקו או יחזרו בהם אם יש
בעדותן דופי. kedei sheyishtoku o yachzeru bahem im yesh be'edutan dofi. If
there's some flaw in their testimony, if they're making it up, we
have interrogation techniques that will reveal when a person is lying. That
is, putting them under a bit more pressure and stressing them out
is going to make... we know this from cop shows and the
CIA and things like that. People get the good cop, bad cop.
So those types of techniques putting pressure on the witnesses will get
them to reveal when they're lying. Okay. וצריכים הדיינים להזהר בעת חקירת
העדים שמא מתוכן ילמדו לשקר. Utzerichim hadayanim lehizaher be'et chakirat ha'edim shema
mitochan yilmedu lasheker. But the דיינים dayanim have to be very careful
not to lead the witnesses by revealing too much information that might...
make it so that they could get through even if they're lying.
And then the רמב"ם Rambam says בשבע חקירות בודקין עדים b'sheva chakirot
bodkin edim exactly like our משנה, mishnah, seven חקירות, chakirot, and then
he goes on after the list of seven ומכאן החקירות יתר על
השבע. umikan hachakirot yeter al hasheva.
And then after the seven חקירות chakirot there are other questions which
also count as חקירות chakirot as well. So I mentioned before it
seems like in משנה תורה Mishneh Torah the רמב"ם Rambam groups the
additional questions as part of the חקירות chakirot category, but in his
commentary on the משנה mishnah it seems like he puts them in
a separate category. So it's an interesting question and maybe more of
a theoretical question but also about how how what the implications are
for making a mistake in the questions about like, oh, I didn't
I don't know which עבודה זרה avodah zarah he worshipped, but I
saw him worshipping עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Well we can't execute you
for that. So is that because it's a חקירה chakirah that's even
more more basic quality of the testimony, so those are interesting questions.
Okay, the גמרא Gemara says מנה הני מילי? mena hanei milei? Where
is this learned from? מנה הני מילי mena hanei milei usually introducing
a point of which פסוק pasuk provides the source for this. So
how do we know there's a פסוק pasuk that teaches us the
principles of דרישה וחקירה? drishah v'chakirah? So אמר רב יהודה דאמר קרא,
amar Rav Yehudah d'amar kra, רב יהודה Rav Yehudah the אמורא Amora
tells us that it's based on this פסוק, pasuk, actually three different
פסוקים, psukim, some of which from last week's פרשה parsha and some
from this week's פרשה. parsha. ודרשת וחקרת ושאלת היטב. v'darashta v'chakarta v'sha'alta
heiteiv. So first the פסוק pasuk by עיר הנדחת, ir hanidachat, it
says ודרשת v'darashta you investigate וחקרת v'chakarta and you cross-examine or you
search even further ושאלת היטב. v'sha'alta heiteiv. So that sounds like three
different points that is number one ודרשת, v'darashta, number two וחקרת, v'chakarta,
and number three ושאלת היטב. v'sha'alta heiteiv. You have to ask very
well. So those are three. ויאמר והוגד לך ושמעת ודרשת היטב. v'omer
v'hugad l'cha v'shamata v'darashta heiteiv. This is about someone worshipping עבודה זרה
avodah zarah with also last week's last week's פרשה parsha
that it is told to you and you hear about it ודרשת
היטב. v'darashta heiteiv. So ושמעת ודרשת היטב v'shamata v'darashta heiteiv or just
ודרשת היטב v'darashta heiteiv is one. ויאמר ודרשו השופטים היטב. v'omer v'darshu
hashoftim heiteiv. And the judges have to investigate very well and that's
regarding the
in the case, sorry, of עדים זוממים edim zomemim which is in
this week's פרשה. parsha. So ודרשו השופטים היטב. v'darshu hashoftim heiteiv.
So how do we get this? ואימא חדא חדא
כדכתיבא.
v'eima
chada chada k'dichtiva. So maybe we should say each one of those
three examples is just one. That's רבי יוסי'ס Rabbi Yosi's position, that
you only need three חקירות, chakirot, not seven. Okay, דאם כן לכתבינהו
רחמנא בחדא. d'im kein l'chitivinhu rachmana b'chada. But no, maybe the תורה
Torah could have just written them all together in one requirement that
in general there's a requirement to do to do דרישות drishot and
would have listed three all together. כיון דכולהו בהדי הדדי כתיבי מהדדי
ילפי.
keivan d'culhu bahadi hadadi ktivi
mehadadi yalfei. Because they're each written in a separate context we can
apply them generally to learn out that there should be seven. That
is three and two and two adds up to seven.
וכיון דילפי מהדדי כמאן דכתיב בחדא דמי. v'keivan d'yalfei mehadadi k'man d'chtiv
b'chada dami. It's like they're all written together because that is it's
in three different הלכתי halachic contexts so maybe I wouldn't know that
I have to have in general for a capital crime seven חקירות,
chakirot, but the fact that there's sort of this overlap, this is
kind of like a בנין אב binyan av sort of, but it's
sort of different because what we're saying is we're trying to draw
from three different פסוקים psukim and kind of splice them together to
create the number seven. That's the דרשה drasha that's being used and
we're going to see it gets a little bit okay. דילפי מהדדי
כמאן דכתיב בחדא דמי. d'yalfei mehadadi k'man d'chtiv b'chada dami. So it's
like it's all written together. והלא דמי להדדי. v'halo dami l'hadadi. But
these cases, these three different cases are not similar to each other.
That is עיר הנדחת ir hanidachat and
עבודה זרה avodah zarah and עדים זוממים. edim zomemim. So why are
they different? We have a סימן, siman, פל"ט סיי"ף התר"ה. Palat Sayif
Hatra. So עיר הנדחת להנך תרתי לא דמיא. ir hanidachat l'hanach tarti
lo damya. עיר הנדחת, ir hanidachat, an entire city turns to עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah,
is not similar to the other two. Why? שכן ממונם פלט. sheken
mamonam palat.
That is in a case of worshipping עבודה זרה avodah zarah or
in a case of עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, your money is safe,
but for an עיר הנדחת ir hanidachat the property of the inhabitants
of the city is incinerated. Now עבודה זרה להנך תרתי לא דמיא
avodah zarah l'hanach tarti lo damya and עבודה זרה avodah zarah is
not similar to the other two, שכן בסייף, sheken b'sayif, because עיר
הנדחת ir hanidachat and עדים זוממים edim zomemim in a case of
murder, both of them would be executed by beheading with a sword,
but עבודה זרה avodah zarah is execution by סקילה, skilah, stoning. And
further עדים זוממים להנך תרתי לא דמיא edim zomemim l'hanach tarti lo
damya and עדים זוממים edim zomemim is not similar to the other
two, שכן צריכים
התראה, sheken tzrichim hatra'ah, because the other two require a warning, but
עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, very interesting, almost unique among capital crimes, does
not require any warning in advance. Presumably if you're entering into a
conspiracy to corrupt the judicial system and bring false testimony against someone,
that's already sort of we assume that you're you're
warned enough about that, or maybe it doesn't need you to be
warned because it's such a corrupting crime, things like that, so fundamentally,
doesn't require התראה. hatra'ah. So each of those three has a unique
quality, that is עבודה זרה avodah zarah execution is by סקילה. skilah.
עיר הנידחת, ir hanidachat, the property is also destroyed and the עדים
זוממים edim zomemim doesn't require התראה. hatra'ah. So each of those three
means we can't combine them together as one construct to learn שבע
חקירות. sheva chakirot. So how do we do? Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says בהיטב היטב ילפינן מהדדי וגזירה
שוה
מופנה. beheiteiv heiteiv yalfinan mehadeidi ugzeirah shavah mufneh. So what do we
do? No, each of the three contexts uses the word היטב. heiteiv.
So we can make a גזירה שוה. gzeirah shavah. It's not a
בנין אב. binyan av. It's not sort of a general literary connection
between the three that's the דרשה. drasha. It's actually more precise. We're
using the word היטב heiteiv in each of those contexts. The word
היטב, heiteiv, right, all three of them say
היטב. heiteiv. So we make a גזירה שוה gzeirah shavah and the
גזירה שוה gzeirah shavah equates the three contexts. So the גזירה שוה
gzeirah shavah tells us that these three can be combined together. Okay.
And that's why בהיטב היטב ילפינן מהדדי. beheiteiv heiteiv yalfinan mehadeidi. That's
why we can combine them together to learn seven. But now remember
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says only three. So it has to be
a דרשה drasha that there could be a debate about. The גזירה
שוה מופנה. gzeirah shavah mufneh. It has to be an open-ended גזירה
שוה. gzeirah shavah. That is, there's a debate about גזירה שוה. gzeirah
shavah. גזירה שוה gzeirah shavah is one of the דרשות drashot that
has the best strength, at least in part because it's almost entirely
informed by tradition rather than by logic. It's just, oh, the same
word appears in two different contexts so we can bring them together,
you have to have a מסורה masorah to be able to use
the גזירה שוה. gzeirah shavah. But what about a גזירה שוה מופנה?
gzeirah shavah mufneh? So what does רש״י Rashi tell us? גזירה שוה
מופנה הוא כדמפרש ואזיל ואין משיבין עליה. gzeirah shavah mufneh hu kidmefaresh
ve'azil ve'ein meshivin aleiha. So גזירה שוה gzeirah shavah that is מופנה,
mufneh, that is,
רש״י Rashi quotes from other סוגיות, sugyot, גזירה שוה המופנה למדים ואין
משיבין. gzeirah shavah hamufneh lemedim ve'ein meshivin. If it's מופנה, mufneh, if
it's left over, that is, it's a word that's extraneous to the
פסוק, pasuk, then the גזירה שוה gzeirah shavah is we can learn
from it ואין משיבין ve'ein meshivin and someone can't disagree. Once we
have that גזירה שוה, gzeirah shavah, it's not up for debate. So
that's a very watertight proof. But how could רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
disagree? So it must not be מופנה. mufneh. So that's part of
the question. דאי לא מופנה, de'ee lo mufneh, if it's not מופנה,
mufneh, איכא למיפרך, ika lemifrach, then someone could disagree with this position.
ואיי פנויי מופנה דהוה ליה למיכתב. ve'ayei pnu'ei mufneh dehavah leih lemichtav.
So how in what sense then can we claim, the initial claim
will be that the word
היטב heiteiv is מופנה, mufneh, is an extraneous word in the פסוק.
pasuk. So how is it extraneous? So מדהוה ליה למיכתב, midehavah leih
lemichtav, it could have been written ודרשו וחקרו. vedarshu vechakru. It just,
they have to investigate. Doesn't have to say היטב. heiteiv. They have
to do it very well. ושני קרא בדיבוריה בהיטב. veshani kra bedibureih
beheiteiv.
The פסוק pasuk uses the word היטב heiteiv specifically, שמע מינה לאפנויי.
shma mina le'afnu'ei.
So the reason why the word היטב heiteiv was used is to
be open for use in the דרשה. drasha. ואכתי מופנה מצד אחד
הוא, ve'achati mufneh mitzad echad hu, but isn't that only מופנה mufneh
that it's only open-ended, that it's an extraneous word from only one
side of the גזירה שוה? gzeirah shavah? Not on all of the
פסוקים psukim don't have that same solution to make it an open-ended
דרשה. drasha. Okay, so בשלמא הנך תרתי מופנה. bishlama hanech tarti mufneh.
So two of them are מופנה. mufneh. That is, two of the
use of the word היטב heiteiv are extraneous because it says ודרשת
וחקרת. vedarashta vechakarta. Okay, משום דהוה ליה למיכתב. mishum dehavah leih lemichtav.
אלא עיר הנידחת, ela ir hanidachat, but
in the case of עיר הנידחת, ir hanidachat, which is the first
case, the first פסוק, pasuk, מאי הוה ליה למיכתב? mai havah leih
lemichtav? How could it have been written to not use the word
היטב? heiteiv? הא כתיבא כולהו התם. ha ktiva kuleihu hatam.
So it could have been written in the case of all of
them, התם נמי אפנויי מופנה. hatam nami afnu'ei mufneh. And since in
the other two the word היטב heiteiv is extraneous, that's enough, ומדהוה
ליה למיכתב דרוש תדרוש umidehavah leih lemichtav darosh tidrosh or חקור תחקור.
chakor tachkor.
It could have used a double לשון lashon because we know doubling
the same verb in the תורה Torah is a use of the
Hebrew language often used for emphasis. So instead of saying ודרשת וחקרת
היטב, vedarashta vechakarta heiteiv,
it could have said דרוש תדרוש darosh tidrosh or חקור תחקור. chakor
tachkor. That is, it could have used a doubling rather than using
the word היטב. heiteiv. ושני קרא בדיבוריה בהיטב. veshani kra bedibureih beheiteiv.
So the פסוק pasuk went out of its way, God went out
of His way to use the word היטב heiteiv to open it
up for a דרשה. drasha. שמע מינה לאפנויי. shma mina le'afnu'ei. So
it must be that it's open for interpretation. Okay. So that is
so far the claim. Now this seems a little bit we have
to do a lot of work to prove that the word היטב
heiteiv is extraneous such that the גזירה שוה gzeirah shavah will be
an impervious גזירה שוה. gzeirah shavah. If it's a גזירה שוה מופנה,
gzeirah shavah mufneh, then it will be impervious to attack. So that's
sort of the argument up until this point is to claim that
the word, the word היטב heiteiv has been extraneous in every context.
Okay. ואתו נחנקין בקל וחומר מסקילין ומהרוגין. ve'atu nechnakin bekal vachomer miskilin
umiharugin.
So maybe we can learn נחנקין, nechnakin, those executions that are done
by strangulation חנק, chenek, can be learned by קל וחומר kal vachomer
from stoning and beheading.
ואתו נשרפין בקל וחומר מסקילין ve'atu nisrafin bekal vachomer miskilin and שריפה.
sreifah.
Burning is learned from קל וחומר kal vachomer from stoning. So that
is once we've learned it in the case, right? The cases that
those three פסוקים pesukim are dealing only with cases either of הרג
hereg executions or סקילה skila executions. There are two that, or one
is primarily by הרג, hereg, עיר הנדחת. Ir Hanidachat. There's one primarily
by, only by סקילה, skila, which is עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. And
then עדים זוממים Eidim Zomemim is sort of an open game because
it depends on what kind of a crime you were trying to
accuse the person of. But and you could learn the other two
executions by קל וחומר. kal vachomer. But הניחא לרבנן דאמרי סקילה חמורה.
haniicha lerabbanan d'amri skila chamura. That only works according to the Rabbis'
position, which is that stoning is the worst, is the most severe
punishment, most severe capital punishment. אלא לרבי שמעון דאמר שריפה חמורה, ella
l'Rabbi Shimon d'amar sreifa chamura, but Rabbi Shimon thinks that burning is
the most severe execution. So מאי איכא למימר? mai ika l'meimar? How
could Rabbi Shimon learn שריפה sreifa cases that they require דרישה וחקירה
drisha vechakira by קל וחומר? kal vachomer? We would say, oh, maybe
שריפה sreifa you need something else because Rabbi Shimon thinks that it's
actually... now it's interesting, what's the קל וחומר? kal vachomer? The קל
וחומר kal vachomer is if the most severe execution
requires this kind of investigation, then קל וחומר kal vachomer a more
light punishment will require it? That doesn't make sense either. That's חמור
וקל chamur vekal almost. So it sort of gets to be what
are we saying, what's the קל וחומר? kal vachomer? It's almost like
the קל וחומר kal vachomer is for a more severe crime where
we want to punish you, nonetheless you have a requirement of דרישה
וחקירה drisha vechakira which is going to hold us back. So too,
even for a more light crime where we have less motivation to
execute you, even there we'll also have a requirement for דרישה וחקירה.
drisha vechakira. But that sort of seems like the קל וחומר kal
vachomer is a little bit backwards because we're trying to learn from
the more severe punishment to the more
less-weighty punishment. Okay, so how can Rabbi Shimon defend himself? אלא אמר
רב יהודה. ella amar Rav Yehuda. So Rav Yehuda now comes back
with a different דרשה. drasha. אלא אמר רב יהודה והנה אמת. ella
amar Rav Yehuda vehinei emet. So the פסוק pasuk says והנה אמת
נכון הדבר. vehinei emet nachon hadavar. That is, once it says you
did the חקירה chakira and everything, it says we've discovered that the
facts are true. והנה אמת נכון. vehinei emet nachon. That's three. חד
סרי. chad srei. So then we have eleven. That is what? If
you go through the פסוקים pesukim again, it's not just the seven
from before, but we can actually have eleven different words to use
to count for the חקירות. chakirot. And now what do we do?
שבע לשבע חקירות. sheva l'sheva chakirot. Seven of them, seven of the
eleven are used for the seven
חקירות. chakirot. תלת לגזירה שוה. tlat l'gezeira shava. We use three of
them are the word היטב heiteiv which we use for the
גזירה שוה. gezeira shava. פש ליה חדא לרבי שמעון לאתויי נשרפין. pash
lihu chada l'Rabbi Shimon l'atuyei nisrafin. And one of them, that is
we had seven, we had three for the גזירה שוה gezeira shava
and we have one more, there were eleven. So the eleventh one
we use for Rabbi Shimon to include even נשרפין, nisrafin, because Rabbi
Shimon holds that שריפה sreifa is the most severe
punishment. So לרבנן מלתא דאתיא בקל וחומר טרח וכתב לה קרא. lerabbanan
milta d'atya bekal vachomer tarach vechatav lah kra. And for the Rabbis
who could have learned שריפה sreifa by a קל וחומר, kal vachomer,
so the Rabbis actually will even consider the fact that this must
be something which could have been learned from קל וחומר kal vachomer
which the Torah went out of its way to include anyway. A
general principle we have by קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Because קל וחומר
kal vachomer is in general a logical argument,
so then sometimes the Torah includes things which could have been learned
by a קל וחומר kal vachomer anyway. Now interesting, how can we
learn things from קל וחומר? kal vachomer? Shouldn't we say אין עונשין
מן הדין? ein onshin min hadin? So we're not talking about actual
punishment here of אין עונשין מן הדין ein onshin min hadin where
we say you can't learn out punishments from קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
We're in a context of capital punishment and we're discussing the דרישות
וחקירות. drishot vechakirot. That is ways actually to acquit the criminal in
such a case, we would say we wouldn't say אין עונשין מן
הדין ein onshin min hadin because the whole purpose of this is
actually to save the person using
the
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Okay. מגדד בה רבי אבהו. megaded beh Rabbi
Abbahu. So Rabbi Abbahu responds to
Rav Yehuda and says: אימא לאתויי שמונה חקירות. eima l'atuyei shemonah chakirot.
That is, according to the רבנן, Rabbanan, why do you have to
say רבנן Rabbanan that their use of the eleventh word is just,
eh, well, that was something that is also to include שריפה? sreifa?
They could have learned שריפה sreifa by קל וחומר kal vachomer but
it will be... be included explicitly by the תורה Torah anyway? So
רבי אבהו Rabbi Abahu asks רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, why not say
that eleventh word should be used to learn that there's actually a
requirement for eight חקירות chakirot instead of seven חקירות? chakirot? So wait
one second. So the גמרא Gemara asks about רבי אבהו, Rabbi Abahu,
is there any תנא Tanna who has the opinion that there are
שמונה חקירות? shmoneh chakirot? שמונה חקירות מי איכא? shmoneh chakirot mi ika?
So אלמא לא, alma lo, so maybe we should say there's no
one who says that. והא איכא לאתויי בכמה
בשעה. veha ika l'atuyei b'khama b'sha'ah. You could, meaning what eighth question
could you even ask? Oh, so maybe we should ask how far
into the hour. That is, the most precise measure of time that
they had was hour. Maybe we could even be more precise and
say how far into the hour. We would say in minutes. The
Rabbis have what they call, they had דקין dakin and they had
חלקים, chalakim, but they probably wouldn't be able to measure חלקים chalakim
for a crime, because that's just three and a third seconds. But
בכמה בשעה b'khama b'sha'ah they could ask how far into the hour.
ותניא נמי הכי, v'tanya nami hachi, and we have even a ברייתא
Baraita that actually includes a Tannaitic position that there could be an
eighth חקירה. chakirah. ותניא נמי הכי: tanya nami hachi: היו בודקין אותו
בשמונה חקירות. hayu bodkin oto b'shmoneh chakirot. They would check him with
eight different questions. הניחא לאביי, ha nicha l'Abaye, so that's fine for
אביי, Abaye, אליבא דרבי מאיר דאמר אין אדם טועה אלא כלום. aliba
d'Rabbi Meir d'amar ein adam toeh elo khlum. That's okay according to
אביי, Abaye, according to the position of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that
a person knows exactly what time it is, that is even within
the
hour. ולהך לישנא נמי
דאמר אדם טועה משהו,
u'lhach lishna
nami d'amar adam toeh mashehu, so שפיר. shapir. And even for someone
who makes a little bit of an error, that is within the
hour, that'll be okay also. אלא לאביי אליבא דרבי יהודה, ela l'Abaye
aliba d'Rabbi Yehuda, but אביי Abaye explaining the position of רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda that we saw in the משנה, Mishnah, דאמר אדם טועה
חצי שעה, d'amar adam toeh chatzi sha'ah, that a person could make
a mistake up to even half an
hour. ולרבא דאמר טעו אינשי טובי, u'l'Rava d'amar ta'u inshei tuvei, and
according to רבא Rava who interpreted the משנה Mishnah to mean that
actually people can err even more, right? We saw the way we
understood the משנה Mishnah that רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position even up
to one hour in either direction, which would be two hours, so
מאי איכא למימר? mai ika l'meimar? How could you say that? אלא
לאתויי בכמה ביובל. ela l'atuyei b'khama b'yovel. They could ask you not
only
which שבוע shavua is it, which group of seven years within the
יובל yovel cycle is it, היינו באיזה שבוע? hainu b'eizeh shavua? No,
so you can't ask when in the יובל yovel cycle it is
because that's the same thing as we already asked. אלא לאתויי באיזה
יובל. ela l'atuyei b'eizeh yovel. Which יובל yovel year is it? That
is, which out of the since the beginning of the יובל yovel
cycle until now, which cycle of fifty years has it been? I
don't think nowadays anyone knows that, particularly because already in the בית
ראשון Bayit Rishon period they stopped counting the יובל yovel years it
seems, though there's some debate about that. ואידך כיון דאמר באיזה שבוע
לא בעי באיזה יובל. v'idakh, keivan d'amar b'eizeh shavua lo ba'ei b'eizeh
yovel. So that could be a מחלוקת תנאים machloket tanna'im about whether
or not you should even ask that question. Now obviously once they
stopped recording that, that question falls away and is meaningless because if
no one knows it then obviously it's a question no one can
be expected to answer correctly and we sort of can't ask that
question anymore. But it becomes an interesting question, do we expect people
to know which יובל yovel year it is or not? I'm thinking
there may also be a little bit of a polemical piece there
as well against some of the sectarian groups who cared a lot
about the, we know the authors particularly of the book of ספר
יובלות, Sefer Yovelot, the Book of Jubilees, care very much about which
יובל yovel cycle it is. So maybe that's the rabbinic polemic against
them. Okay.
Yes, sure. So it sounds like the גמרא Gemara is being stricter
about the time than the משנה, Mishnah, is that right?
The גמרא Gemara is stricter about, in other words, the גמרא Gemara
is suggesting as a, so as part of the argument about the
דרשות, drashot, the גמרא, Gemara, רבי אבהו Rabbi Abahu challenged רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda and said, maybe you're going to have to say there
should be a at least a potential position that was rejected that
would have entertained the notion of an eighth question
about the time. But that's more sort of a technical point about
how the דרשות drashot are working and less, it seems like, I
mean again, it sort of gets uncovered at the end, you know,
the scholarship about that would either be, oh this was a ברייתא
Baraita and they discovered it later and they put it in at
the end of the סוגיא sugya because that's a good flow for
the סוגיא. sugya. Alternatively, perhaps a fabricated ברייתא, Baraita, I wouldn't want
to say that usually, but there has been some evidence that often,
in support of a theoretical position, there may be ברייתות braitot that
the sort of conveniently coincide with the position that was just proposed
and there's been a lot written about that recently. Yep.
I just a question about about the Jubilees.
Did you say that was Sadducees?
I'm not sure they're Sadducees, they're some kind of non-rabbinic, it was
very early, it really predates a lot of the rabbinic activity.
Is that the apocrypha?
It's in some kind of apocrypha or pseudepigrapha or something. It's outside
of our תנ"ך, Tanakh, right. That's what I was saying. So the
Rabbis probably were at least somewhat aware of those kinds of ideas,
maybe there's a push against that as well. That's maybe more speculative.
But here at least according to the At least according to the
גמרא, Gemara, at least the main issue is that no one was
keeping track of which יובל Yovel year it was because there was
no יובל Yovel year. Okay.
Did the witnesses have to take an oath before they testified that
it would be truth, truth?
No, there's a basic assumption that if you're coming to court you're
going to tell the truth. It's a whole, it's such a strange
principle in the Western court, right? What do we do? Someone comes
to be a witness, so we say, okay, swear you're going to
tell the truth. Well, I could lie about the oath also. So
the halakhic system uses oaths in various other contexts but not for
testimony. שבועת העדות, Shvuat Ha'edut, the שבועה Shvua about testimony is something
else, about we're going to get to that מסכת שבועות, Masechet Shvuot,
but that's about if someone you know someone knows a testimony that's
going to help you in a court case but they're not coming
to court, how do you force them to come to
court? Okay. So רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yosei omer, תניא אמר להם
רבי יוסי לחכמים. Tanya, amar lahem Rabbi Yosei lachachamim. So Rabbi Yosei
remember said there are only three חקירות. chakirot. So how does Rabbi
Yosei says to the חכמים, Chachamim, לדבריכם מי שבא ואמר אמש הרג
אומר לו באיזה שבוע באיזה שנה באיזה חודש בכמה בחודש? ledivreichem mi
sheba ve'amar emesh harag omer lo be'eizeh shavua be'eizeh shana be'eizeh chodesh
bekama bachodesh? So Rabbi Yosei says if someone comes to court and
says yesterday
I saw him commit murder, yesterday, you're going to still
ask him which year in the שמיטה Shmita cycle is it and
which year in the שמיטה Shmita cycle and which month and which
day of the month it was? אמרו לו, Amru lo, so the
Rabbis response to Rabbi Yosei is דבריך מי שבא ואמר עכשיו הרג,
devarecha mi sheba ve'amar achshav harag, if someone comes to court and
says oh, I killed him today, right
now, אומר לו באיזה יום באיזה שעה באיזה מקום? omer lo be'eizeh
yom be'eizeh sha be'eizeh makom? They're going to ask him, meaning Rabbi
Yosei, why do you limit it only to three questions? Which day
of the week and which hour and which place? That is presumably
within the same week the court case will be dealt with. But
according to Rabbi Yosei, the Rabbis push back. Rabbi Yosei, why if
someone says I saw a murder right now, why would you even
ask him anything? אלא אף על גב דלא צריך, ela af al
gav delo tzarich, even though it's not necessary, רמינן עליה. raminin alei.
It's part of the formal proceedings of the court to impose these
questions on the witnesses. כדירבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Kidi'Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar.
It's like the opinion of רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar. הכא נמי אף על גב דלא צריך, hacha nami af al
gav delo tzarich, so because he said even the case where it's
unnecessary we impose רמינן עליה, raminin alei, כדירבי שמעון בן אלעזר. kidi'Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar. That's the opinion of רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar,
which is in the case,
sorry, one second, I'm trying to find in רש״י. Rashi.
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, להטריחם. lehatricham. We sort
of like what I described earlier from the רמב״ם, Rambam, it was
in the previous פרק, perek, להטריחם דאמר מסיעין היו את העדים ממקום
למקום. lehatricham de'amar mesin hayu et ha'edim mimakom lemakom. They would bring
the witnesses from one place to another. That is part of the
formal proceedings of the court to put pressure on the witnesses. So
pressuring the witnesses often means asking them interrogative questions even though the
answer is obvious. Like, if they came today and said it happened
today and I ask you what day of the week is it
and what day of the month was it and things like that,
is just to put pressure on them and to kind of intimidate
the witnesses to make sure that they're not lying. So it's not
because the question is actually necessary. Okay. רמינן ליה כדירבי שמעון בן
אלעזר. Raminin lei kidi'Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. Rabbi Yosei, so Rabbi Yosei
has to defend himself. Rabbi Yosei says אמש הרג שכיח לרוב הדיוט.
emesh harag shachiach lerov edyot.
So yesterday he committed murder, that's a even in there, that's a
somewhat common occurrence for a testimony about a case that happened today.
עכשיו הרג, Achshav harag, if he killed him today, לא שכיח לרוב
הדיוט. lo shachiach lerov edyot. That's not something that is really going
to show up in a normal kind of testimony. So Rabbi Yosei
is willing to say that that's not a good challenge to his
position. We'll stop there now and we'll try to do a few
minutes of ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. Maybe we don't have the time but we'll
see.